welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
the check-ins yeah I feel like I don't
know whose nervousness has a different
quality to nervousness and whatever word
you'd want to put on that it's about 10%
maybe 15% feeling playful like I want to
kind of tickle Justin in an impropriety
on that my wife just made me a delicious
hamburger and I'm feeling a little
sluggish so welcome to the stoah I am
Peter Lindbergh the Stewart of the stoah
and a Stowe is a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge of this moment and we
are very lucky today to have the based
philosophical badass himself Justin
Murphy and yeah Justin first came on my
radar like a couple of years ago he was
like talking about like having sex with
dead bodies and I was like this guy kind
of like looks like me but of course like
better-looking and more intelligent in
whatnot but like okay so this guy's
pretty cool I've been following his
career and it was it was pretty
delicious career to follow and so me and
him have been trading e-mails back and
forth to get each other on each other's
like podcasts and whatnot we never had
made it happen
so we made it happen and I'm also part
of his indie thinkers community which is
quite awesome so definitely check that
out and hopefully he will maybe plug it
near the end so I'm gonna hand it over
to our emcee for the day for the Q&A
Raven the lovely Raven so raven if you
can take it from here
thank you Peter so as per usual we will
have Justin speak about the cynical
enlightenment I am very excited to hear
what you have to say about this for
about 20-25 minutes and then we'll move
into question and answer period I'll
warm Justin up or Peter and I will warm
gestern up with some questions and then
we'll be taking questions from the
audience and then today at the once the
session is over we're actually going to
do another like sense-making session for
this where we'll go into breakout rooms
and just talk freely about the different
ideas that came up in the session so
looking forward to that as well
and with that Justin unmute yourself sir
manage my time and if it's not too much
to ask if you wanted to maybe give me
like a five-minute warning at the five
minute mark that would be good but if
not that's okay to set it for I'll set
it for 20 minutes and that's good to
know I can have 25 if need be I'll aim
for 20 that's great well first of all
I'd like to thank Peter for the
invitation I'm truly grateful and I'm
sincerely happy to be here you know at
first when Peter invited me I mirrored
actually because I've spoken with Peter
a couple times privately and he's a very
calm and balanced man and you know I'm
just not I'm prone to terrible bouts of
enthusiasm and well you know my haters
would call that narcissism and perhaps
their right to some degree and frankly
honestly I didn't want to blemish Peters
what I'm sure is a very healthy
discussion group here unless I was
confident that I really had something
valuable to offer and that's honestly
why I kind of ignored Peters invitation
for a few weeks and so then I dragged my
feet but then an idea came to me and I
emailed Peter and I said let's do it and
so I thought that what I might offer to
a venue called de stoah is a set of
reflections on a particular lineage or
tradition within which stoicism sits and
I think it's not a very well-known
tradition or lineage in fact as far as I
know it's never really been formally
diagnosed in any published literature
that I'm aware of so I will be
presenting a somewhat novel or original
hypothesis today and I only have 20
minutes so needless to say it's going to
be limited to hypotheses and assertions
which I'm not going to be able to fully
convinced you of or fully justify but I
can at least lay them out there for you
and you can take them or leave them and
we can discuss them and so I would call
this tradition or lineage the cynical
enlightenment although really we should
spell that with a K and not a C this is
a very confusing set point which I won't
get bogged down in but basically the
term cynicism as we know it today means
something totally different than what
I'm going to talk about it has to do
with the kind of weird kind of
historical a set of historical
inversions really I'll give you the
backstory real quick at the time of the
Ange
Synnex people like Diogenes of Sinope
the the haters of Diogenes would call
Diogenes Kanako's with a k' or I've had
that hard sound to it and that's
actually one of the roots for what we
now call cynicism has that heart that
heart K sound and what it meant at the
time was dog like that's technically
what what it meant in ancient Greek in
the ancient Greek dog like so it was an
insult it was an attack on Diogenes for
acting and living like a dog so it's
that doglike sense of cynicism rather
kinases 'm that I'm going to be talking
about today and it's not what you think
of when you think of soft sea cynicism
and in the way that that's used today so
just a bit of a clarification before we
begin and I think that just the main
thesis I'm going to offer you today is
simply what I take to be the main thesis
of this tradition the kind of underlying
implicit argument or idea that I think
characterizes this this long-running
tradition and then I'll give you a very
rapid fire narrative of what exactly
that historical tradition involves the
main figures I think it involves and
this is where I might confuse many of
you because I I'm going to give you a
lineup of thinkers that you've probably
never heard put in one lineup before and
it's going to go from the beginning with
Socrates all the way up to kind of post
1968 left libertarian radical politics
and Western societies so that's my kind
of overarching vision and I'm going to
kind of just take you through these
arguments and this historical tradition
really really rapidly obviously I'm
gonna be condensing and simplifying like
crazy so if anything I say seems way too
quick or insufficient it probably is
right I'm just trying to pack as much as
I can into a fun and hopefully
stimulating 20-minute talk so all right
I'll start with the major thesis I would
say or the underlying core idea of what
I'm calling the cynical enlightenment or
rather clinical enlightenment and it's
something like this I'll present it to
as a very simple kind of syllogism the
idea is that a social group cohesion
requires falsehoods
almost by definition necessarily if you
have a group that is persisting over
time that group is going to tell itself
certain lies we see this in very mundane
examples right this is not a very
provocative or sophisticated argument
just think about everyday small talk
right think about everyday niceties
think about the people you live with
your partners your roommates whatever it
might be to get on with people right you
have to kind of agree to overlook
certain things right and in a controlled
small-scale way that's very healthy
right this is good it's nice to do this
it's kind to do this and it is genuinely
good for for it for group cohesion for
for getting along for having a community
it's necessary and so that's a one level
of analysis so that's at one scale at
which it's obviously you know the right
thing to do to not constantly be looking
for every little truth you possibly can
about the people around you in your
community that would clearly become
quite unhappy quite quickly now the
problem is though when you have the
falsehoods that hold together social
groups play out over time at larger
scales this actually becomes one of the
core problems of of complex societies
and I would even argue and I see as
implicit in this tradition the idea that
as society becomes more complex
precisely what is most bad or evil about
large societies is essentially rooted in
these falsehoods that have their source
in kind of social niceties and social
cohesion okay and so ergo social groups
it's eventually realized are on some
level invested in evils that they don't
fully understand because of these kind
of small scale compromises we have to
make with the truth to get along with
each other those kind of blossom or or
balloon into these complex circuits of
hypocrisy and deceit and this becomes
the the kind of festering ground for so
much of what we now see as so horrible
and problematic about about any kind of
complex society whether that be
inequality or injustice
or the perpetuation of propaganda all of
these things that it's very common for
people today to to to lament about
complex societies there is a realization
in this tradition I'm calling the
clinical enlightenment that everything
that's wrong with complex societies this
is essentially rooted in these small
micro dishonest E's that we that we
submit to in our everyday interactions
for the sake of of what is essentially
social pressures of getting along in a
community okay and so the final
implication of this perspective is that
ergo one should live and act or at least
some people within society and perhaps a
tiny minority within society needs to
live and to act in a way that looks and
is rather radically antisocial and they
have to do that in a way that involves
speaking the truth recklessly but there
is this realization running from
Socrates all the way up to you know
Western left liberalism in kind of the
late 20th century that that kind of has
always intuited this this fact that to
to really get under and break up the the
falsehoods and dishonesty is that that
structure our society you need at least
a small number of people who quite
recklessly or just going out into the
world and saying all of those things
you're not supposed to be saying which
by definition make that person an
asshole by definition saying these
things you're it's not just that you
appear to be unreasonable or you appear
to be mean or nasty or or gross or
perverse or whatever negative adjectives
you can come out but it's not just that
you seem like that you actually are you
actually have to bite the bullet that
you are actually engaged in what is
essentially antisocial behavior and and
so that's the tradition that's the main
thesis of this tradition it's I
presented I presented to you today as a
kind of syllogism a set of realizations
followed by a kind of implication for
for social action as having an
essentially redemptive value okay and
what I'll do just now is kind of go very
rapid fire through some
the milestones in this tradition and
maybe before I do that very briefly I
want to just point out one other little
watchword if you will of this tradition
a particular concept that you actually
see emerge in in the literature as I'm
going to kind of piece it together for
you and it's this concept of Parisi
I've talked about this a few time given
some talks on this I've written about it
and it's something I've been I've been
very interested in for a long time this
this is a Greek word and it's often
translated into English as Frank speech
and by the way there's a really good
book by Foucault probably fucose the
best book by Foucault is called the
courage of truth and it's pretty much an
analysis of apprecia the concept of
presenting in the ancient world and so
this is kind of the watchword that
actually was used by multiple people in
this tradition that I'm about to to tell
you about Diogenes also had a similar
concept called defacing the currency
I think it's essentially the same thing
okay and I talked actually at some
length in other talks and I've written
also a little bit about the mechanisms
of prea like what exactly is required
for priests yet to function I talked
about this and the base tool is lectures
for instance so I'm not going to go into
that here I'm gonna focus on kind of
expanding out the the historical
narrative okay so so it all starts with
Socrates in my understanding most of you
know that the famous stories of Socrates
this is required reading and in many
universities say you we all know that
Socrates was put to trial for corrupting
the youth and you know Socrates MO was
he what did he do he walked around and
asked people really annoying questions
all of the fucking time and he wouldn't
stop they called him a gadfly and
ultimately you know if you simply go
around society asking difficult
questions a little too frequently that
really does become a crime that's kind
of the lesson of Socrates it's kind of
interesting that it ultimately gets
diagnosed that's corrupting the youth
which is actually somewhat you know we
can that we can think of some
interesting kind of contemporary
analogies to that it's like I won't go
into that but um yeah so so if you ask
too many questions too annoyingly you
you actually really are a kind of Public
Enemy
and as we see in the case of Socrates
that is often weirdly linked to
to some sort of touching some sort of
sacred thing and and and the youth has
always been a kind of sacred space that
that no reasonable adult should show to
have anything to do with corrupting the
youth right so that Socrates right it's
obvious we all know that story so that's
an obvious kind of form of parisa and
people hated him for it and and they
essentially put him to death for it um a
lesser known figure in the in the the
Golden Age of ancient Greece is Diogenes
biology's is this amazing extraordinary
character many of you might have heard
me talk about him elsewhere he basically
engaged in these kind of extraordinary
provocative public acts he he basically
acted like an animal and it's really
quite bizarre if you look over the
anecdotes the types of things he would
do like masturbate in public or you know
he one time took a shit on the stage of
what we're essentially the the kind of
Olympic Games at that time in ancient
Greece and he basically was what we
would now today call a performance
artist I mean just a wild man who would
go out doing extremely weird provocative
things just to prove a point
really and he also lived a very simple
life so he kind of put his money where
his mouth was he lived out of a barrel
and had very few needs really kind of he
ate very simply he relied on nothing had
almost no objects or belongings and was
very isolated socially also so he didn't
have many friends but he was able to
kind of speak the truth but not just
speak the truth lived the truth in a
kind of provocative way and and I think
the best way to understand Diogenes is
that his target was kind of budva
hypocrisy right because you know ancient
Greece is kind of the the beginning of
Western civilization as we know it so
there are starting to emerge some some
comforts right some luxuries and kind of
lifestyle comforts and with that with
kind of booze walk comfort there's
always hypocrisy and he was basically
trying to call out Greek society on on
its hypocrisy
maybe it's worth pausing for a minute if
that's not absolutely obvious what I
mean by how hypocrisy or falsehood is
kind of baked into civilization itself
I'll pause on that real quick I think
the best way to think about that is just
the concept of manners right what are
manners manners are essentially a kind
of deception where you actively try to
present yourself in a way that is other
than what you naturally are inclined to
present yourself right so it's a kind of
real
really it's kind of subliminal did how
should I say kind of diffuse diffuse
form of lying essentially and so he's
kind of attacking Western hypocrisy at
its core when were first starting to
develop these kind of pretenses and kind
of bodily forms of lying okay and so
he's just attacking his and this is what
a true philosopher does just like
Socrates asked too many questions
he refused to refuse to stop and search
with the truth same thing with Diogenes
but Diogenes took it to a new level
because for him it was performative he
was actually engaging in in activities
that were performative ly provocative so
I see it Diogenes is kind of learning
from the mistake of Socrates Diogenes is
like I'm not gonna get put to death for
asking the youth too many questions I'm
just gonna do crazy a shit and it's
gonna get the point across whether they
like it or not and it's harder to punish
them for and in fact Diogenes was really
quite clever because there actually was
a real political advantage to his
techniques relative to Socrates because
not only did Diogenes avoid getting put
to death like Socrates unfortunately
failed to avoid but he was quite
powerful because of it Alexander the
Great for instance is famous for having
said that if he could not be Alexander
he would wish to be Diogenes so rather
extraordinary right so it's a real
testimony to that the real empirical
mechanisms of apprecia as actual
political activity that really does
change distributions of power in a
certain way okay and so next up comes
Jesus Christ and the Stoics which are
you know both both of these kind of
phenomena are very close in time so it's
a little difficult actually to tease out
which is causing which but one thing
that you all might know about the Stoics
is that or you might not know is that
the stoicism is one way to understand so
stoicism as it emerges is that it's kind
of a kind of amused waz Amal is one way
of putting it of cynicism of ancient
cynicism a kind of becoming bushwa of
ancient cynicism because as you know the
people the great Stoics like people like
Marcus Aurelius
these were governors right these Marcus
Aurelius was was a Roman Emperor
and in stoicism was a kind of polished
up cleaned up version of what Diogenes
really introduced with cynicism and
that's well documented in the literature
it's not just me saying that there's a
clear kind of inheritance there okay but
the main difference being that it Marcus
really some people like that fit the
insight of Diogenes in a way that works
for rulers and governors okay so that's
that's an important little mutation
there but Jesus Christ also is
essentially participating in the same
tradition and there's a really good
passage in the Gospels of Mark for
instance where Jesus actually uses the
word parousia um he it's when he's he's
basically at the time I think it's Peter
at the time is saying to Jesus hey you
know we like your message and all but
you maybe don't need to run around
letting all of the governors here are
you saying that right because you know
they're gonna kill you right so Peters
kind of like you can say all this it's
great you should develop this and we
should organize around this great idea
you have Jesus but maybe just don't go
out of your way to let the government
hear you sang it and what Jesus says in
response is no that's part of the point
that's part of the project here and he
invokes this word parisi uh so so it's
really it's really quite fascinating I I
really do think there's gospel evidence
that Jesus had some kind of conscious
kind of conscious participation in this
lineage that goes from Socrates to
Diogenes up to Jesus and the stoat and
the Stoics and and and of course people
like Marcus Aurelius I'm quite confident
would have some sort of awareness of
this tradition but they were governors
and they have to kind of make it
respectable and and and they they
significantly modified the the
implications of ancient kinases 'm for
you know to make it fit for rulers okay
so just to kind of move forward a little
bit more rapidly and this is where my
diagnosis i think becomes somewhat
idiosyncratic this is where maybe a lot
of scholars who are very familiar with
these different historical periods might
kind of raise their eyebrows at me so
I'll just give you that kind of honest
caveat there but then again that's in
part you have to keep in mind because
just very few scholars do this kind of
truly kind of cross historical type of
analysis so I'm just being honest with
you that I'm not aware of any kind of
scholarship that at the at this moment
supports what I'm saying but I'll make
the case to you
I'm gonna fast forward a lot in part
because of my own historical blind spots
I I don't I'm not very familiar with
much work from from the Middle Ages and
the Dark Ages but one figure I am quite
familiar with is jean-jacques Rousseau
and I see Rousseau as this kind of
extraordinary reinvention of this parisi
astok tradition I don't know how much
you know about Russo's life but a truly
truly extraordinary intellectual figure
and say what you want about his ideas
and whether they're true or false or
good or bad but as as a biography he's
an extraordinary example of a truly
committed radical intellectual a man who
clearly was going to give his whole life
to thinking the truth as well as he
could and expressing it as fearlessly
and as radically and in a political way
as he possibly could no matter what
might befall him he basically spent most
of his life on the run from various
governments actually and often in debt
you know had this kind of really wild
life where he basically just always
prioritized his ideas developing his
ideas and publishing his ideas
constantly getting into trouble for them
and constantly running away from whoever
was out to get him often you know I'm
talking about like actual kings and
queens of multiple countries he was
banned for multiple countries and and
and he was wanted by multiple
authorities and so without going into
Rousseau his ideas too much we'll all
I'll say is that if you look at how he
practiced his ideas and many things he
said also his autobiography in
particular Rousseau you might not know
this basically invented the modern
autobiography it wasn't really a thing
until until the idea of setting out on
paper a long series of kind of
comprehensive soul-searching reflections
about one's life no one ever really did
that and he and he did it in this big
way and he went specifically hard on
trying to find things that were
embarrassing things that were kind of
shameful and of course another another
example would be a st. Augustine right
who's kind of known for also talking
about things like masturbating right so
so there are other kind of figures I'm
skipping a little bit but Rousseau had
seem to have this insight that if he
could simply be as radically honest
about himself as possible if he could
find all of his own hypocrisy
all of his own evil by essentially
introspection and
and basically just shamelessly and and
selflessly laying bare all that is kind
of evil in his own feelings and
aspirations and psychology he had this
idea that that would be kind of so
explosive that it could really lead to
cultural progress rapidly that it could
have revolutionary political
implications for making the world more
equal and more free and and this
actually works I mean again I'm really
interested in peer achill mechanisms and
if you look at the influence of yourself
it was extraordinary right oh sorry
about that so I'll finish up in five
minutes
at five minutes max I mean I'll try to
be quicker than that
and so Rousseau has this kind of crazy
idea and lives this crazy life of
philosophical kind of self punishing in
some way and it actually does have
profound effects because lo and behold
the French Revolution
is well documented as as flowing in in
large part from the ideas of of Rousseau
many of the leading French
revolutionaries were in fact influenced
by Rousseau and and there's documentary
evidence of this okay so in some ways in
some ways what I'm talking about it's
really not just abstract ideas it's it's
it's a kind of mental model of how
public philosophy works that as far as I
can tell in history actually does
produce real ripple ripples in the
social fabric okay and and and Rousseau
is just kind of one of the more recent
kind of modern examples in some ways
Rousseau kind of opens up the modern
period culturally and politically okay
and so I'm gonna just really
fast-forward through through the next
few but just to put it on the map for
you I many of you will know that I'm at
the time quite interested in ile de luz
and I think in his own interesting weird
way des loves is also participating in
this tradition because de las actually
was quite interested in stoicism and he
cites the Stoics quite frequently in his
in many of his books actually and I
talked about in my book on Dilla's I
talked about his interesting
relationship to Christianity I think de
les is actually much more Christian than
people realize as I'm saying now he's
more stoic than than many people realize
and finally I would argue that the kind
of 1968 moment for those of you who
don't know 1968 was this kind of
extraordinary
period millions of people went on
general strike in France for instance
and a lot of people in 1968 genuinely
believed that Western Western societies
were actually going through legitimate
economic and political social
revolutions and I would argue that there
is to this day a kind of latent left
libertarian revolutionary politics that
has not really been fully explored yet
this is my politics that I'm interested
and this is as far as I see the world as
far as my beliefs go my politics are my
ideology I mean I think intellectuals
should try to have no ideology but to
the degree that I have won to the degree
I have a politics it's this kind of
subterranean hiding latent radical left
libertarian parisi astok politics and I
think you can draw a straight line from
Socrates all the way up through all of
these people to envision what it might
look like for us to speak and think and
live and act in a way that has a kind of
left libertarian flavor or style but it
essentially seizes on parisa as a form
of revolutionary political action and
that to this day is what I'm mostly
interested in and in my own way that's
that's that's the the philosophy that
I'm trying to figure out and live with
my own life thank you so much excellent
thank you very dense and super exciting
so I'm gonna invite people to put their
questions in the chat I just initially
would love for you to kind of break
apart each of the words in what you just
said so latent left libertarian you kind
of got into Layton but you can you
describe more of like what left
libertarian means to you and how you're
embodying that tradition near your own
life yeah sure I mean frankly I wouldn't
want any of this to get too bogged down
and left and right I think it's it's
super epiphenomena and I think there's
so much confusion around it right now
that I would almost rather just do away
with it but to answer your question I
mean what I'm essentially suggesting is
that this spirit I characterize for you
this parisi astok spirit I do think that
it has a kind of intrinsically left-wing
flavored vibe to it because it is
essentially a kind of insurrectionary
attitude it's a kind of instruction or
ethos and it's militating against
injustice in a kind of provocative
disruptive and radical way so I'd say
that that most clearly aligns with what
we today think of as as a leftist kind
of ethos and but but it's it's quite I'm
saying its latent meaning hidden or not
yet cultivated it's not yet revealed to
use a kind of hi to Gary and phrasing if
you will it's it's it's latent or hiding
simply because of accidental contingent
factors of up the public culture today
and I think the only way you really kind
of reveal it or unconcealed it is
through this kind of what appears to be
a kind of radically antisocial type of
of activity and I'm trying to kind of
show you all or make the argument that
sometimes you might see certain
performances that appear nasty or mean
or or unreasonable or antisocial but in
fact you might want to support that type
of thing you might want to encourage
more of that that might be exactly what
we're lacking today Peter I see you have
some questions would you like to ask yes
first I did I love that talk man I was
brilliant and I'm really appreciative to
of you coming in like being really
considered like talking about something
well stoicism most people come into
talking over their fuck they wanna talk
about so I really appreciate that
so the question of this per easier thing
and maybe we can put like a more norm
Norma term to it like revolutionary
truthfulness if you will and then you
used you mentioned reckless truthfulness
I'm wondering if there could be two
versions of this revolutionary
truthfulness one that is a reckless
version and one that is reckful like a
wreck if that if I can use a tortured
word like reckful truthfulness do you
think that's a possibility it's
definitely possible but my instinct is
that the the conscious careful version
of pre Xia is precisely the government
version it's the rulers version and and
and that's essentially going to have a
kind of conservative disposition and
perhaps you're right Peter but perhaps
there are times and places for both and
maybe that is the most productive way to
think about it but what I would argue is
that there's we have a lot of this kind
of conservative parisi a going on right
now because we have a lot of elites who
say one thing in private and they say
another thing in public this is this is
all over the place and I think I think
that kind of conservative or careful pre
Xia it it doesn't have the same kind of
disruptive progressive fun
it's often it often can be a kind of
selfishness with a kind of pro-social
gloss right it's like I I I know what I
really think but I don't want to talk
about it in public because it's gonna
hurt people's feelings
so it's framed as like I want to be good
to society I want to be nice I don't
wanna be a bad person so I'm gonna keep
what I really think in my head whereas
in fact that's that's a very selfish
kind of rationalization which is what's
really going on is that person wants to
maintain their own security and comfort
and control with the truths that they
know and they're not willing to take the
they're not willing to pay the cost the
the social opprobrium of really putting
it out there in public so here let me
see if I can yes and that so one thing I
really like this idea like this slick
sort of like the noble lie of keeping
these white lies right that helps the
social cohesion yes um and it's like one
case in point I've been talking about
this lately is especially in the work
world it's like how you doing today I'm
good
like what the fuck does that mean right
no no one's good like I'm like I'm on a
roller coaster of emotions these days
and I'm just one of them's not good but
it's just the word to just kind of like
the nice and easy so you in streak and
instrumentalize the person forever the
fucking one instrumentalize and for so
it's just like one example why we're
telling each other these these like
white lies but so I don't know if you
notice that I was a trainer right I'm
still a trainer and the Dale Carnegie
Training the Highland friends and if
most people been around 400 years so
with all those social fluency and shit
like that and there's something called
meta communication where you not just
talking about the content where you can
jump outside of the content and talk
about maybe the asymmetrical intentions
that are involved in that conversation
and then you can call it out in such a
way that it's tactful and you allow the
other person to say face they don't get
triggered and then you can put dumb and
yourself at the edge of your thinking
together but you have to have that kind
of social attack in order to do so and
so that's what I guess when I'm
gesturing towards for a potential of a
reckful truthfulness okay I like that
yeah I didn't know Dale Carnegie was so
based but that works I think I think
this is an interesting avenue for
research and for experimentation kind of
figuring out micro tactics where people
can
kind of explore this frontier of
reckless truth-telling but in in clever
ways that perhaps don't need to be as as
explosive and as and as crazy as as
someone like Diogenes there could
totally be a whole menu of tactics and
strategies for introducing this type of
a style to your life and this type of
adventure without being as crazy as
Diogenes and perhaps you just cited one
example yeah and the seduction comes to
mind but maybe it's a conversation we
can bookmark for another time so I'll
take Raven back in for the Q&A cool yeah
just I'm kind of wondering like there's
seems to be some sort of dispositional
like thing going on here as well like
especially these characters in history
where they had to incur such a high cost
for for taking these radical positions I
mean especially Socrates right so and I
and I think like especially on the
Internet there are people who are just
kind of antagonistic who just find each
other and are just being kind of
outrageous I think Ron mentioned this in
like a immature kind of disagreeableness
versus like a mature kind of
disagreeableness do you have anything to
say in terms of like being sure that
you're being truthful because there's so
many levels of delusion possible like
you may go after some sort of idea or
some sort of consensus without even
examining yourself in terms of whether
or not you're really being honest yeah
it's a really really good question and I
think you're absolutely right that
there's a lot of cultural activity going
on right now which might even fancy
itself as having this kind of chemical
kind of quality to it but in fact it's
just seething bad faith and resentment
playing itself out and kind of
destructive circles and yeah I think
there is a very very difficult line to
walk on in the Christian tradition this
is you know why they call it the
straight and narrow path it's hard right
you there pitfalls on both sides in the
delusion register it's it's like how he
talks about de territorial ization and
and he talks about
I he's at pains to point out that
there's kind of pitfalls on both sides
it's this really difficult delicate
balance that you have to walk and so I
completely agree I think that's that's a
huge question a huge problem I'm not
sure that I have an amazingly impressive
solution to the puzzle but I can say I
can say one or two things one is that
there's a really really amazing book
probably I think one of my favorite
philosophy books I've ever read in my
life by Peter slaughter Dyke I called
the critique of cynical reason and it's
if you're interested in the stuff I'm
talking about with cynicism and kinases
omits pretty much the best place to go
it's it's a it's a it's a massive book
it's an extraordinarily interesting and
complicated kind of theoretical
historical tale that he tells about the
evolution of cynicism and it's where I
learned most of what I know about
cynicism so most of what I told you
today about cynicism kind of came from
that book and I think one would need to
reread that book I think that book has
answers to this question but but in
short it's something to the effect that
kennis ism has kinases amande modern
cynicism had this weirdly kind of
volatile character where it's very easy
for Kinnison to flip into cynicism and I
think something like that is going on
with the kind of resentful bitter
destructive kind of trolling
truth-telling
that you see on the Internet today to be
a little bit more specific just to try
to give you something of concrete value
and not just a hand wave like I kind of
M up until now I would say one
characteristic that that is a pretty
reliable differentiator between
resentful trolling cynicism and
truth-telling radical Cantus ism would
be paying a price under your own name so
if you look at what some of the worst
behavior online right now it's by
anonymous people it's by trolls right
and there's this big debate in the kind
of radical intellectual circles of like
should you go should you write on the
internet under your own name or should
you write on the internet under an
anonymous or pseudonymous name and I
think this is this is a really concrete
answer to your question because I think
so long as you are writing under your
own name or so long as you speak
under your own name and you are paying
the price for what you say and what you
do it's much more likely to be the real
kind of criticism that we want more of
whereas if you're insulated and it's
only some pseudonym on the internet that
is associated with your provocative
truth-telling
you're probably not doing it right and
you're probably using that it's like
that pseudonymity is actually preventing
the parisi
from having its effects on the social
fabric and it's actually locking it up
into this little box that's
self-contained and then that that that
that kind of antagonistic energies just
circulates within its own little system
and it never really touches the social
fabric and that would be my hypothesis
because you need you need to have skin
in the game that's right
you need skin in the game and you also
need feedback loops you know to make
sure that you're on track and I just
have an avatar that's doing all of that
work for you you don't have that real
interfacing with the real and incurring
the actual social cost of being truthful
and I think maybe the problem with the
question is that like honestly it's
something you have to take
responsibility for there's no
prescription for how to do this it's
like you have to do your own radical
truth-telling where you're incurring a
kind of cost and see where that takes
you and yeah great those are very
precise OnPoint additions to what I was
saying absolutely correct I agree with
all that
yeah mimetic paper question would you
like to I guess this is sort of almost
what was just asked but what happens
when chemical parousia goes mimetic I
couldn't the countercultural and some
cultural movements of the 60s and 70s be
viewed this way and also isn't that what
culture war II is like that's maybe one
way of viewing culture war yeah for sure
I mean I think that there is a
consciousness a self-consciousness from
the very beginning that Priya has a
memetic quality the whole point of doing
these kind of ridiculous performative
truth-telling actions that someone like
Diogenes did was because he knew that it
would percolate beyond him rumors would
spread right images and stories and
anecdotes would spread well beyond him I
think he knew I didn't he knew that very
well and that's something I mentioned at
the beginning of my
talk was that Diogenes had a very nice
little phrase for what he was doing he
called it defacing the currency and
that's a really fascinating and rich
label I think for this type of activity
because what is currency on some level
currency is mimetic right it's on when
when you I think what he was basically
trying to say was that any social order
basically has a set of values right and
and those and those values are
determined in part by all kinds of
social nonsense right whose valuable
who's popular who's liked who's not
there is a kind of hierarchy of social
value which is not at all founded in
truth and it's biased in many different
ways right
and currency like the capitalist economy
money as we know it is is part and
parcel of this kind of arbitrary fake
kind of value system right and but he
seem to believe that if one acts out the
truth in this kind of profound way that
causes a that brings a cost on the
performer or the speaker that in this
weird way it has this any luck table
quality of decreasing the value of the
fake currency in other words defacing
the currency as we know it but of
introducing a new type of value you
might even cite Nietzsche's
transvaluation of values you might even
put Nietzsche in this tradition I think
that would be quite reasonable and and
and I think the essence of that
mechanism like why does that work how
does that work is essentially what we
now call mimetics so that would be my my
best shot at an answer to that question
excellent Tyson would you like to and
meet yourself and share your story sure
thank you yeah so my story is this
morning actually recorded a video sort
of directed towards some of the things
I've been thinking and feeling about the
you can say like the mimetic tribe of
the Great Awakening it's like queuing
honors anti Bill Gates I have a lot of
like people of this mindset in my my
circle my past friendships and all this
so my video was directed toward them and
it was things I knew would be triggering
to people people leave that I even know
personally and like respect and love as
people might think I'm talking directly
to them and get upset and so I recorded
this and it helped me get a lot of
clarity in my thinking and that felt
good to really have the process of
thinking for myself and express some of
my thoughts and then I chose not to
share the video simply because I knew a
lot of my motivation for then posting it
was like this excitement of the drama
that it might stir up and then also the
people that would like affirm me and be
like yeah like we're on your side we
like this and so I think what this is
helping me do is like just I want to
refine sort of my internal compass of
what to share when to kind of rein it
back and just keep it to my own process
and then also connecting this with we
had Brad Blanton on yesterday talking
about radical honesty um so yeah I'm
just curious a little bit about that
like your internal compass for you know
when is it when you feel that call where
there's like a responsibility to to
share and to express that truthfulness
or when do you find yourself like sort
of reining it back in keeping it to
yourself mmm it's a great question
really great question I mean I I would
never pretend to be able to give advice
on this sort of thing so this is a type
of question every person irreducibly has
to answer for themselves so with that as
an important caveat I can tell you
certainly a bit about my thought
processes and how I think about that but
I would never want to give this as
advice because these are essentially
existential puzzles you know these are
essentially decisions that individuals
have to make in the in the dark without
without any kind of guardrail and
different people's situations are going
to be very different but what I would
say is one
I thought about listening to your story
is that I think it's a it's a it's a
very healthy instinct to think you know
after you make a video or after you
write something to think you know am i
doing this for the right reasons and if
and if you fear that maybe you're doing
it for the wrong reasons to hold fire
that's that that's certainly an
honorable thought process but on the
other hand I sometimes think about
everything I'm talking about as a way of
kind of channeling some of the base
desires that we have not based but base
you know the lower appetites and the
lower desires that we have I I wonder if
the the kind of philosophy I'm
developing here is is a way of
channeling our base animalistic desires
or appetites in a way that is productive
so for instance I mean when I sometimes
when I make videos when I write blog
posts or when I tweet stuff or whatever
I definitely can feel a kind of lust for
the drama a lust for the reaction I find
it fun of course and and I want that and
I would be lying if I said that wasn't a
motivator for me but my my answer to
that is that we are essentially animals
and we do have base based desires and
base appetites and I think part of life
is the kind of spiritual practice of
reigning those in of course and
controlling them and and and not being a
victim of your of your appetites or base
desires but they're not going to
ultimately go away and if you have this
kind of perverse drive to literally
stamp them out you're just going to be
um one of those like terrible morbid
Christians who you know that's a that's
a that's a that's a bad path that that's
that's the incorrect in many ways it's
even a sin it's like scrupulousness so
there are ways of being like too morbid
and to Christians such that it's
actually a sin in its own right and and
so I think that there is actually a way
of just kind of owning up to your base
desires and of course we want a little
drama of course we want a little bit of
excitement we want adventure we want a
little bit of recognition as human
beings as thinkers as as whatever and I
think if you're okay so that I'll just
wrap that up by saying the key ultimate
criteria that I always go back to is
really just one thing everything begins
and ends with this one thing is do you
really believe what you're saying is
true if you do you really can't go wrong
putting it out there
you can you can cause all kinds of
damage to your life and inconvenience
and and difficulties for yourself and
your family and friends for sure but
when it comes down to is it the right
thing to do ultimately if you really
believe what you're saying is true or
what you're writing or speaking is true
it's never ever ever wrong to put it out
in public that's what I believe that's
that that's what I always default him
thank you very much yeah definitely I
would say to that and I'll just say this
it I guess is that like the the idea
that you you have to take a risk right
but you're also incurring a cost by
creating drama like what you're saying
Justin when you have your face on it and
it's your friends and that you're
stirring up all of this with it's not
just attention that you're getting
you're getting a lot of inconvenience
and that's like the feedback loop that's
the loop like you change the environment
that you're in you get new feedback and
you actually have to manage the drama
you have to figure out how to navigate
it and that in a way is actually like
teaching you whether or not you were
right did you actually truly believe
this thing because if you do you're
willing to fight for it and you're
willing to put the work in but if you
are like shit I really wish I hadn't
have done that I don't feel like dealing
with all of this that's a sign that
maybe there's a misalignment and a kind
of delusion but there's a theme that's
coming up in the Stowe about thinking in
public and I think that this this is
part of what you're talking about Justin
as well had one quick practical thing to
the to the question I was just asked
very briefly on unless you have a huge
audience by the way none of your friends
or family are ever gonna care about what
you say or be offended by I just want to
add that like I I mean I have a I don't
have a huge audience at all but I have a
decent audience and I've been saying
pretty wild stuff for a long time and
I've never once had an actual friend or
family member ever come to me with
anything that I made or said and feeling
upset or or anything like that there
have been a couple times where like
something I said blew up and went viral
and people in my life have heard about
that and then maybe ask me about that
but short of that and that's very rare
you know you don't have to worry about
some blog post or some video actually
making its way to any of your friends
and family in fact if anything the
problem you'll experience will be why
are none of my friends or family ever
even hearing about this or caring about
this question and I'm not exactly sure
how to approach it but it does kind of
get back to this dispositional thing so
you know there it tends to be
dispositional differences in men and
women
and women tend to not be as oriented
around risk-taking and I'm kind of
wondering about what do you think about
bringing women into this I know that
there are some figures out there like
like Ayla is a great example of a woman
who just like speaks the truth but how
do we get women to take on this idea of
like speaking truth to power and just
exposing themselves when there is risk
involved and there may be a tendency to
be more risk-averse in general it's a
good question it's a very good question
probably a better question for a woman
to answer but my instinct is I don't see
any particular need for any type of
positive project or intervention to
increase the proportion of women doing
this sort of thing I am if that's
something you're interested in then I
support you and you should try to figure
that out but I don't see I don't see any
reason why any kind of gender inequality
on on who's doing this I don't see it as
necessarily being a problem yeah it
probably does select for this type of
activity probably does select for for
men but as you said there will be women
who who do it too for sure so yeah I
don't I don't really I don't really see
why you would need to correct that
imbalance personally but I mean if
probably if you wanted to do that if
that's something you're interested in it
would probably just be a matter of
developing this philosophy and a a kind
of language that is more a tradition
that women are interested in right so
I'm sure there are feminine I'm sure you
could tell the historical narrative I
told through women right I mean I'm sure
they exist but as I said the tradition
or the lineage I tried to paint for you
today is sort of subterranean enough
finding the the female equivalent of
this tradition which I'm sure exists on
some level it's probably even more
subterranean but it might be a good
research agenda and by illustrating that
and showing how it works that could very
well bring more women into the fold of
this type of experimentation perhaps for
sure well okay we have one more question
here and I'm gonna read it out loud for
this for Brent okay so this is what he's
saying in the comments I agree with
everything you Justin are saying in
theory in fact I offered to Peter to do
stoah on cynicism Kinnison before I knew
you were doing one but I see you as
somewhat of a left reactionary and you
even identify as libertarian but I think
you are no Socrates and have limited
social solidarity and concern so my
question is why are you averse to mass
politics particularly the Bernie Sanders
movement which at its core is about
parasya so there's a lot there I'll
start with kind of just the end bits
which is that I'm not against mass
politics I just believe that mass
politics is essentially at odds with
true philosophy or truth-telling or even
true science any type of truth seeking
and mass politics are are at odds if you
are going to play a game of mass
politics you are going to be lying in
one way or another now it's with maybe
just the the indirect exception of kind
of reframing this kind of chemical
politics I'm talking about
you can reframe it as a kind of mass
action right because I am ultimately
interested in how can truth-telling
individuals create desirable ripples in
the social fabric so in that ways in
that way I am still interested in mass
politics I am still interested in
essentially revolutionary politics so
I'm interested in overthrowing
institutions I really am I'm interested
in overthrowing this rotten false order
that that defines our our life today
it's been one of my abiding interests
and passions ever since I came of age
it's figuring out how to overthrow all
of this all of this that's so rotten so
in that sense I remain highly invested
and highly interested in a kind of mass
politics but what most people mean by
mass politics like organizing other
people to try to change something it's
just at its core it's going to require a
certain amount of lying as I try to kind
of sketch earlier and I don't think
that's necessarily bad I think that's a
part of life for sure but if you're if
you're pursuing a kind of intellectual
vocation then you can't engage in that
kind of mass politics is my short answer
to that kind of long question I I know
I'm kind of ignoring some parts of the
question but I just kind of chose to
respond to what I most immediately had
something to say about thank you I'm
curious if brent has a follow-up to that
22 okay do we think we can get this last
question
Justin if it runs over a little bit at
the hour you okay I'm fine no problem
okay great so Michael would you like to
admit yourself massive question sure
maybe I can give you guys a bit more
background one sec I try to video yeah
so I'm actually teaching a course at the
birthing Montreal in innovation
management and I'm in front of that
challenge of trying to tell through a
bunch of people you know that their
future is compromised you know like I'm
always know like I think that dilemma of
how can I get a message true how can i
how can it you know how I can deliver
something in such a way that the
audience will get it digest it and do
something about it and not just you know
I think that barricades of preconceived
believes you know that that won't make
the message effective and I like talked
the waiter I thought about it was to try
to make activities in such a way that
they would you know find information
themselves and make their own conclusion
I would like to hear you talk on that
well my instinct is to try to think of
something you can do in your actual
personal life that incurs a cost for you
and then share that with them or tell
them about it or bring it up or find
some way to work that in because I think
ultimately that that's one of the real
concrete lessons of this Prezi astok or
clinical tradition is that unless unless
you can materialize and embody your
ideas in some kind of way that you're
willing to pay a price for until you can
do that it's always going to be in this
ethereal abstract realm of cheap talk
and I know this is hard depending on
your situation and your context there
may very well not be any particularly
obvious ways of doing this so I
recognize it's not necessarily the most
easy or practical advice for some people
in certain situations but then again I
also think there are many
ways to do this there are it's not
impossible to come up with even small
ways right um in some ways like in some
ways the practice of kind of
vulnerability is kind of a low-level
example of this maybe maybe this is
something people in this crew are kind
of into you know every time you if
you're giving a lecture in a classroom
or you're presenting yourself or
addressing yourself in any context
anytime that you kind of drop the guard
a little bit and you share something
that most people wouldn't really want to
share in any in any time you do that any
any time you kind of give that gift of a
vulnerability it's a kind of
self-sacrifice it's a kind of paying a
cost it's like volunteering to pay a
cost and that almost always produces an
effect of being more trustworthy about
actually touching people of actually
making them wake from their slumber and
think huh this guy must be for real and
and I think that's so that would that
would be my kind of high level
suggestion of looking for ways to incur
a cost and then conveying that I think
it really does just put everything
you're saying on to a new level but even
if you can something even if you can't
do something grand like masturbate in
public you can at least find some way to
be vulnerable or something like that in
your in your everyday interactions to
make them kind of more radical and real
well here we are at the end thank you so
much Justin this was so juicy well thank
you so much for having me I'm genuinely
very grateful to be here and I'm
delighted I'm always delighted I love
talking I love to have an opportunity to
share my ideas so thank you all thanks
to you guys and go definitely and yeah I
want to invite anybody who wants to stay
for half an hour afterwards to talk
about this I certainly have a lot of
ideas so I would love to hear like from
the audience so that's an invitation
awesome
hang around for a little bit I have a
meeting in like a half hour but I'll
hang around for a little bit I'm gonna
get a little bit of water than be right
back cool
so before I press stop recording let's
make a few announcements and then we're
gonna have like a 30 minutes that's
making sense making session
so before the announcements just in my
friend beautiful thanks for coming on
the suit again there and and we do like
cool things here like Socratic
speed-dating like we're even actually
designed that weird speed-dating method
with us our credit inquiry so I'm very
interested for some kind of
cross-pollination with indie thinkers
and the stoah so maybe we can jam about
that another time
well upcoming events the shame
breakthrough at 6 p.m. with AJ Vaughn is
happening and I just was interviewed
actually Dave fuller on behalf of rebel
wisdom about the conspiracy theory
narrative that's coming online with q1
on and how to navigate that for him as a
sense making journalists so you can
check that out that just got released is
pretty cool and he's coming on a Tuesday
at 1:00 p.m. to discuss that with us
here and the snow is based off a gift
economy if you're inspired to provide a
gift to the stoah or myself as a Stewart
just go to the WWF slash gift alright
everyone thanks so much